folks so in the last
lecture in the last lecture we talked
about the human hand and you were all
supposed to have watched this video from
this uh medical class on the anatomy of
the human hand uh which is an incredible
instrument with like 21 degrees of
freedom so today what we are going to do
is to learn a bit about how uh robot
hands have been built and people have
been doing this for de kids but the most
recent entry is the leap hun from our
friends at CMU so Kenny Shaw an and
Deepak I mean Deepak used to be a
student at berlyn okay you've got their
opening slide and uh what they're going
to do for the next half an hour is going
to take us through uh the various uh
choices in robotics hand design and
their own solution for this so with that
take it away all right thank you jendra
so um okay so I think I should mute
here okay um yeah
so let's uh dive in
so you guys already looked at um the
human hand and like it's it has a lot of
degrees of freedom um it's very suited
for Tool use and so on and what we want
to do is
in robotics is to replicate this
capability in uh like Hardware so what
we'll talk about today is what are the
design principles when you go about
doing this so there are broadly two
categories we want to talk about the
first is kinematics so how should we uh
design the joints of the hand in what
positions should we place them such that
we get maximum
dexterity and the second aspect is
mechanics so once we have this design uh
how do we actually build it reliably in
Hardware what Hardware components do we
use what designs do we use so I'm going
to talk about kinematics first and then
can you will go over the mechanics part
of
it the most important part of the human
hand is the opposable thumb so if you
look at um the two major kinds of grasps
there are the power grasp and a
Precision grasp and in both of these
cases for a grasp for a successful grasp
you need to apply opposing forces on an
object to get Net Zero Force
and that's what makes for a like that's
how you can place the object stably in
your
hand and the opposable thumb allows
exactly this it allows the application
of force in opposition to the fingers
and without an opposable thumb um
there's no way you can um stably grasp
these
objects how do we quantify so how do we
quantify Thum posability let's say you
building you have like 10 designs of
robot hands and you want some way to
compare these how do you go about it so
one very useful heuristic is to look at
the common volume that is reachable by
both the thumb and each finger so the
larger the common workspace the more the
thumb opposability because you can apply
opposing forces in a larger
space so here's like a visualization
what you can do is you can sample points
in the workspace um of in the workspace
of the hand and see if these points are
reachable by both the thumb and each
finger so here we have work spaces for
the pinky for the middle finger and the
index
finger and of course you can compute uh
the volumes of these spaces and the
higher the higher the volume the better
better like more um more use of the
thumb you
get the second aspect is
dexterity so workspace doesn't provide
the full picture what you want is how
how dextrous the fingers are in various
position so in each at each posture how
um how many directions you can move the
fingers so let's look at a simple uh
simplified finger so here it's a finger
with just two
joints and in with some joint angles
Theta 1 theta2 and some position
XY now what happens is that if you give
each of these joints some velocity you
get some velocity of the IND Defector
and these are related uh by the Jacobian
so r dot velocity of end Vector is the
Jacobian time Theta
dot now what we want is to figure out
what are the achievable what velocities
can the end Vector achieve for some set
of theta dot so let's say that you you
can for some Theta dot with the norm
less than one what is what is the
possible set of end effective velocities
and the larger this set the more
dexterity you have in this particular
posture
so if you look at this this Theta dot
less than one corresponds to a sphere in
this space and uh if you multiply by
Jacobian this is a linear transform so
it stretches or squishes this space so
what this means is that this set
corresponds to an ellipsoid um and you
can compute the volume of this ellipsoid
which corresponds which is proportional
to the determinant of the jobian times
the choban
transport and these ellipsoids are
called manipulability ellipsoids
so you can plot manipul manipulability
ellipsoids for fingers in different
positions and this is a very useful way
to debug what is going on in your hand
design so for example in this these are
two different hand designs and they
differ by uh how the mCP joints are
oriented and we'll talk more about this
later on in the presentation but you can
see how this impacts manipulability for
the index finger in these particular
locations you can also plot the
distribution of manipulability volumes
across the workspace so here um the
intensity of the color at each point
represents the volume of the ellipsoid
at that particular point and you can see
that for the hand on the right uh
towards the middle of the Palm you get
very little manipulability whereas on
the left you get more manipulability so
this implies that the left design uh is
better than the right right one at least
as far as this dexterity metric is
concerned
okay so these are like two principles
that I talked about as far as kinematics
is concerned um and then Kenny will talk
more about the mechanical
aspect Co thanks
an yeah so I'll talk a little bit about
joint and actuation design so how do we
actually create these robot hands to
match these parameters and try to
replicate the human hand in its
functionality so one of the most common
designs you'll see out there um they'll
use the motors directly as joints in a
robot hand so what that means like you
can see on the top right these motors
are basically chained together to form
the joints of the hand themselves so the
servos like usually have Motors and a
gearbox and an angle sensor and are just
packaged together as each piece of the
finger and the output of the servo shaft
directly drives the joints of the motors
and you'll see this in many hands um
leap hand does this algro hand and Dem
Manis hand have commonly been used and
used this design
the good news is this is very easy to
produce you take the servo Motors you
chain them up and you can control them
very easily however the main problem is
that strong Motors are really big which
makes the robot hand really big and if
you use really small motors they
typically very much too weak and also
the structure the kinematic design
typically is dictated by the motor size
so you'll get like really bulky and boxy
hands and this is really as you know saw
in the lecture this is not how the human
hand works a lot of the strength of the
human hand comes from our wrist tendons
a lot of our actuation doesn't actually
happen inside our hand itself but the
power is transferred
out so there's been you know a lot of
work in mechanical space of trying to
figure out how to transfer the power and
one of the most common ideas it's a four
bar linkage and the idea is you have
like four revolute joints and you'll
have one of them that's actuated by a
motor and another one that's fixed in
place and you can see you know on the
gripper in the bottom right if you do
something like that when you actuate it
you know the fingers will open and close
and you can Define the motion at the end
effector in post form way using forward
kinematics and you see like Inspire hand
or psionic hand will commonly use this
design um and you see this in research a
lot as
well and the nice thing about linkage
design is it's very reliable and
accurate um you know what de motor angle
you get and the fingertip position is
very easy to calculate however you know
the linkages don't have that much
compliances compliance and you know when
you smash the fingers on the table
sometimes the linkages will break or
they'll slide off of each other and
these small components can be very Britt
and it's also hard to make linkage hands
with many degrees of freedom if you
think about the Inspire hand or the uh
you know psionic hand they typically
have five or six degree of Freedom Which
is far less as a n said The more degrees
of freedom you have you know the better
manipulation you can do and often these
hands are very limited to only five or
six degrees of
freedom so then you know many people are
looking at well how can we get more
degrees of freedom into a small space um
and you know tendon driven hands have
been very popular recently what they do
is you take a motor you put it you know
usually into some part of the wrist or
somewhere lower in the hand and then you
have these you know fishing line or some
sort of rope that is connected to the
servo motor and connects up to the
fingers themselves so as you spin the
motors the tendons change in length and
it will change the finger in open or
close it this is sort of similar to how
human tendons work in a sense you have
the actuation further away from the hand
and then you transfer it through some
you know a
tendon so once you make this tendon well
then you have to actuate certain joints
and these joints are passive now but
they still have to be actuated and
there's different design choices on
these joints so one common one is a
revolute joint and as you can see like
you know on the top right and you're
very you've seen the revolute joint a
lot you know in door hinges um it can
rotate in one axis and then every other
axis is fixed so it allows just a very
simple rotation and you would think this
is the obvious uh choice of design and
you see many hands the Dex hand uses
this um but the main problem is it's
very brittle to out of axes forces so if
you take like a you know like a hinge
and you try to bend it in different
weird axes like you bump a hand on the
table um these joints will often break
or they'll uh they're very brittle if
you think about your human hand the
fingers do you know have a revolute
joint in some sense but they're also
able to slide around and that's what
allows our fingers to not break all the
time and that compliance is very
important so you've seen a lot of recent
research where they're looking at how to
improve this and give that compliance in
a a joint but also make it very strong
at the same time
so the next you know category we've seen
a lot recently is rolling joints um so
the rolling joints basically allows for
that joint you know when it gets hit
hard or when it's in contact with
objects to move around and conform
around the object itself so you know the
like you're looking at the fave hand on
the top right um what they do is these
these joints are basically you know
rolling contact which means that these
little pieces will move across each
other and they're connected by rope and
that means you know when they smash
against the table there's not actually
one revolute joint but there's many
degrees of freedom that there's some
compliance in and the fave hand does
this if you see in a flex hand in the
bottom right see how they're moving it
around and those joints are still
compliant and they're moving around they
not breaking and these sliding contact
surfaces you know they're very hard to
design and they often have a lot of
friction but the good news is that
they're very compliant for a lot of
contact which hands often
experience you know we've also been
looking at this idea of a compliance in
our lab um and one of the things that
you know we've seen a lot of is the idea
of a living hinge or flexor joint so if
you think about your shampoo bottle you
think about the lid um that little piece
of plastic in the middle is acting as a
joint so when you open and close it even
if the lid is all one material you're
still able to move uh you know open or
close your lid of the shampoo and we're
thinking about doing that in hands as
well you can use you can design hands
with flexor joints where it's rubber
that you know moves around when you
actuate it with motors and this allows
for some translation and you know
non-actuated axis motion and the soft
material can be casted or 3D printed and
can be very
flexible intended to become very very
popular um you know even with the
rolling contact joints or through you
know flexor joints I there are many many
hands that do this now the shadow hand
is famous from open AI result from many
years ago and we've also been doing some
work in the tendons area we'll talk a
little bit later about our own Dash hand
that we hand V2 because tendons are you
know easy way to get the motors away
from the hand make the hand nice and
small and get still pretty
strong and you know there's one last
category that of hands that we've seen
recently is hydraulic robot hands um in
this case you have like a hydraulic
fluid it's pumped into a reservoir at
very high pressure and then the idea is
that fluid can be pushed through to hand
itself and actually different joints
within it so as you can see on the right
this is the Clone hand unfortunately
there's this pump and all these valves
that maintain it it's very hard to
maintain but this is very cool work in
the sense that you can make something
very strong and the Hand can be very
comp compact in humanik and it looks
very very cool though it is very hard to
control this and maintain it and create
this system but it's something that
people have been working on in future
research so I'll pass over to 8 talk a
little bit about some of our work um
looking at different types of joints in
robot
hands so um is work we did like two
years ago this is Open Source Hand um
which has the motors directly on the
joints it's completely rigid um but it's
still useful for many machine learning
applications which we talk
about so as I talked about in the
beginning mCP joint design can have a
big impact on how um how dextrous the
hand is human beings have humans have
like a ball joint on the mCP the mCP
location but ball joints are really hard
to make uh so typically what's done is
you add two Motors one after the other
at the mCP location and the axes and
Order of these motors are typically very
important so let's take a look at two
hands on the here we have the algro hand
and what happens is because of the
design of the mCP joint in the in the
extended position The Joint loses a
degree of Freedom so when the finger
spins around the fingertip position
doesn't actually change so that degree
of freedom is completely useless so in
the power grph position uh you lose a
degree of
Freedom there's another hand called the
cand which has a different axis um at
the mCP joint and this has a different
problem so while it doesn't lose a
degree of freedom in the extended
position it loses that degree of freedom
in the curled position um and what this
leads to is bad dexterity at in
Precision grasp
positions in leap hand what we did uh is
we changed the order of Motors at the
mCP joint and what this leads to is this
universal joint mechanism where we never
lose a degree of TR uh so if you look at
these two other hands what these hands
have is the motor that controls the
rotation around the finger axis comes
before the motor that controls the
flexing um you press press next yeah
yeah so what that means is that there
will be some pose for the finger in
which the rotation axis gets aligned
with the finger axis and in that
particular POS you hit a singularity um
and the finger loses a degree of freedom
but what we did in the Deep hand is we
switched the orders of these motors so
that the like the motor which controls
the left to right movement of the finger
occurs after the motor that controls the
flexing and what this leads to is that
we this the the axis of uh the rotation
never aligns with the finger and so we
never lose the degree of
fre so we actually see that this leads
to benefits on the metrics I outlined
above so we get higher opposability
thumb opposability volumes higher
manipulability volumes and practically
speaking we are able to to do tasks
which require inhand rotation at the
fingertips as well as inhand rotation in
this power grass position both of the
tasks work really well with the leaf
hat and because the hat is completely
rigid um you can actually easily model
it in simulation so there's this open
source uh specification of the hand
which you can put inside a simulator and
train with large scale RL so as an
illustration we train this inhand Cube
rotation policy and the interesting
thing is it's because it's trained with
learning uh and it gets a history of
joint angles it can implicitly estimate
the state of the cube so there is no
perception it just uses a history of
joint angles to estimate the state of
the
cube cool thanks an um you know part of
the thing about putting motors as a
joints it's very important what motor
you choose um so for us we found you
know the the most uh like strongest and
the lowest cost you know motor that we
could find it also had the servo and all
the angle sensors in it and we made we
very very easy design and very very
strong so it's been one of the you know
easiest to use robot hands in the
category of motors and the joints and we
show a bunch of different results here
um you know this is me doing telop from
one webcam and we're able to do telop on
a bunch of different tasks um just by
using one webcam and we beat you know
the legro hand Baseline pretty easily on
these
tasks and we also soci autonomous
results as well so here we use some
internet videos we pre-train it to get
the robot give the robot an idea of what
the human hand motions are in the videos
and then we use that as pre-training and
then fine-tune on fop demonstrations and
we can see that wean can perform a
variety of different
tasks um lean has been the leading open
source robot hand right now it's really
the best first intro into robot hands
and there's a really big lean Community
around it there's many Works dexc cap is
one of my favorite Stanford and there's
you know over 100 available and I know
at Berkeley there's one also in jenders
group and also uh and a couple others at
Berkeley as well
however um as you can see there's still
a gap between robot hands and human
hands you look at your human hand on the
on the left and the leap hand all the
way over on the right the leap hand is
still a little bit bigger and we're not
really emulating the skeleton and the
skin of a human hand and we really want
you know still that Dexter's kinematic
structure we got from wean but also
improve on the different grass types we
can
make so one of our first attempts at
this was looking at the tend IND design
there's many robot hands out there we
tried to make our own so you can see on
the bottom left there's three different
tendons pulling on different parts of
the finger and these fingers are 3D
printed really easily and there's a
bunch of control that we I won't go into
but how you tension these tendons and
how you control them to know where the
fingertip is is actually quite difficult
you can see on the top right the nice
thing about hands like this when they're
soft is that you can bounce them on the
table and they don't break this is a
real concern with robot hands with all
these different little joints that can
be often
fragile but we found there's some
drawbacks with this naive design um when
you use all these tendons and you have
this flat Palm you lead to pretty poor
grasping like you see this Hammer uh in
the palm and with this flat Palm the
hammer is just sort of sitting in the
fingers it's not all the way curled and
also the softness is maybe too soft you
see the finger can twist in all these um
you know undesirable orientations and
that's good but maybe you don't want too
much so this you know leads us into our
newest work lean V2 um and sort of the
idea is how can we think about you know
how the human has all this bones and
skin how do we combine also soft and
hard material like if you think about
the human hand the bones are giving you
a lot of rigidity and the fingernail
actually helps you with grasping that
fingernail being stiff on the back helps
a lot with your grasping and then the
robot you see in a cross-section of our
finger in the bottom right we also try
to imitate that so the white parts of
that finger are the bone structure and
then the flexure joint is a soft
material in
between and the nice thing about this it
still twists and bends without breaking
and it's really strong and we can 3D
print this all as one piece on you know
multimaterial 3D printers and we came up
with this idea
to do this and I think it's been one a
very strong robot hand it's also very
durable and another thing we introduced
to make the Palm better is we add two
Motors into the Palm so if you look on
the b in the middle on the bottom there
there's this M1 and M2 Motors that
actually actuate the hand to really make
a close really tight and as n talked
earlier the thumb to finger opposability
is very important and by making the you
know the Palm actuating you it increases
the amount of pinch grass that you can
do by a lot and that allows you do a lot
more tighter grasping and better grasp
in a variety of different
tasks and of course you know we're in
Academia we really want to Target this
hand towards ml research so it's still
pretty low cost and easy to assemble and
we'll provide a urdf and telop uh code
for it so I want to talk a little bit
about some of the results on some of our
recent paper we've been working on um
there's been a lot of work in the
humanoid space um in terms of how do you
control robot hands we've also been
using you know a motion captur glove um
you can see Yong here one of our Master
student collaborators he's controlling
our robot hands and the robot arms using
a jell plus glove setup and our Le hand
is nice and soft and it's able to grasp
things like grapes fairly
easily we also SE some autonomous
results doing Behavior cloning um so
these are two weans on our arms and we
train this uh this is diffusion
policy and the nice thing about this is
that because the fingers are soft we see
the plate and the two arms sort of
interacting with the object but we see
that even with them twisting at slightly
different rates or something the soft
hand and the fingers are able to comply
around the object around it and this is
why a lot of people and the robot hand
Community been very interested in
compliant fingers in
general and because you know we have a
human-like SI we can also use things
like
drills which is very hard for robot
hands to do is because the drill is very
heavy and it's hard to press the button
and we can see even autonomously
eventually the policy learns how to
press the button
yeah we show some more results
here you can see even as the finger hits
the table there it's not breaking and
it's you know able to be compliant
towards that uh those
forces we also saw some mobile results
here this is our lean V1 a lot of people
been using lean V1 and we can also use
our motion capture gloves on that system
as well and this is a mobile base that
we built just you know to test out robot
hands more than to actually you know do
a full-on humanoid it's easier for us in
this in this
setting so I think you know we've talked
a lot about the different actuation
designs and there's always this battle
between you know if you want motor
driven design or pendant driven design
um and leand you know very strong and
you know it's very easy because of the
motor driven but you know it's it's a
little bit on the big side and as you
know since showed we can do really good
simulation of it and do simp to real
sometimes the soft hands with the
compliant fingers can be better for
different stuff especially teley
operation but Sy to real can be harder
um but the good news is these hands can
be smaller and more humanlike size and
also I have links to some of our stuff
if you're interested in looking more in
detail on lan.com as well as our decent
uh
work yeah and that's it that's all I
have
thanks you have any questions I guess I
guess we can't hear you guys
um okay now can you hear us yeah yes
excellent so yeah so this is the time
for questions so I think uh people in
the class why don't you just come up to
the laptop and ask your question
somebody must have
questions just
introduce question hey this is my name
is Justin um hey thanks for talking to
us I think the the new lean is super
cool I was gonna probe your you know the
kind of measurement of dexterity of the
Hand by the manipulability I was just
playing with my own hand during the talk
and I realized that I can't actually
move this finger in some of the ways
that your hand can like actuate the last
two joints um and so do you think like
that measure of manipulability is the
correct one to use or do you think like
it it seems like there's kind of a gap
between the conventional sense of
manipulability and how human hands are
actually able to manipulate objects so
can you comment on that a little bit uh
yeah so I agree with you that um like
human hands would not be able to move
your finger in this position um so
that's I would say that's a limitation
of a human hand and it's still desirable
to have robot hands which can do that so
the reason we actually buil this in in
the first place the first iteration of
the hand that we had did not have this
capability and then we tried training
this policy to rotate like very small
objects or like a ball here and it turns
out that's really hard if the object is
um like sort of oblong because you need
need the hand to be able to move the
finger around the object uh so this
particular movement at this Precision
position is very useful if you want to
do like fingertip
manipulation I think the other thing to
think about is when you're actually
grasping When You Close Your Hand your
fingers are actually getting closer and
closer together as you're grasping so by
in some sense you are implicitly having
some of that degree of Freedom as you
close your fingers uh and by adding that
when we do the teleop we're able to you
know spread or put your fingers together
as you grasp and I think it does help
there's always a battle between how
humanlike you want it or do you want it
to be superhuman um and I think part of
it for us is we're giving you superhuman
joint joints in some sense like more
than what a human would have to try to
compensate for the fact that the hand is
obviously bigger um and it's going to
suffer in other ways so it's almost like
I guess a compromise in some sense do
that make sense yeah that's interesting
yeah I have another question if no one
else
say
than thanks
hello uh thank you for the presentation
uh my name is Ethan and
uh hi uh can you hear me yeah yeah yeah
um hi my name is Ethan and I really like
the um demo about the grave manipulation
and
uh um what was like the um policy that
you guys use for it and also is it um is
it just grasping the grape or is it also
like pulling it off from uh from the
stem yeah so
I think that exact task we're doing
telop one of the problems with that
exact task is the robot hand cannot
touch but cannot feel what the the grape
in it um and also the human T operator
actually cannot feel what the robot
hands is feeling there's no haic
feedback to the T operator itself which
actually makes that task quite tricky um
so really the only way we're able to do
that is because the robot hand is fairly
soft and the compliance to the finger
itself is not actually crushing a great
um so you know if we were to look at
touch censors which we are looking at
actually now um the tactile feedback
would allow a policy you know like
action chunking Transformer diffusion
policies what we've been using either of
those um to actually feel the grape
inside and maybe pull in the right way
right now we can only do that Tas tat
but it's something we'll probably look
at soon yeah it's a good question thank
you hi it's me again um I wanted to push
more on this you mentioned tactile s and
haptics um just yeah wanted to get your
thoughts on kind of the state of tactile
sensing for hands and Robotics and then
also haptic teleop
interfaces yeah I think for tactile
itself there you know this gel sight's
been very common on grippers or for like
Allegro hand or lean V1 but the problem
is it's you know it's too big and too
thick and a lot of these sensors are
still really too big um so you know I
think a lot of these film-based sensors
I'm actually looking you know in sort of
to reskin style um very thin magnetic
sensors or or like the resistive sensors
I don't know if you've heard of stag or
some of these other ones that are just
like a resistor basically in a network
and then you can use that um I have't
there's very little work in this area
because I think you have to kind of
solve the robot hand Hardware before you
look at the tactile and tactiles have
you know the sensors have to be very
thin and very small um which makes it
very hard um and I think also like it's
a whole another thing of course to train
a policy to use that data properly which
is also quite difficult I think right
now to collect enough data or to tell y
like Yeah you mentioned haptics um to me
like haptics is very very far away
there's you know there's some very early
stage work in this and there's very
impressive work but it's very very hard
to do and I wonder if using haptics is
sort of the right way to approach a
problem in the sense that if you just
use your human hand and like grasp an
object you can feel it and maybe if you
just wear a you know human touch sensor
glove that's the way you should be
collecting data and doing it or if you
should really be tpping feeling the
haptic feedback through and using touch
sensors on the hand itself um I think
hatic is very hard to set up and very
very expensive right now mostly it's
like air based or fluid based um and it
might take quite a while for us to look
at something like that but I think
tactile centers is more something we're
looking at pretty closely yeah what are
your thoughts on Force sensing like
propri reception within the joint
itself yeah so and N obviously showed
with Cal that the propri reception is
definitely very useful um and of course
this is one of the issue with tendon
driven designs is you you lose some of
that sensing um and I think propri
reception will be useful for a while I
honestly if you if you have it you
should use
it yeah is there other
people hello my name is Amish um I had a
question about the sort of like fault
tolerance that you kind of foresee being
useful in terms of constructing these
hands in the future
so like if you're no if you're have like
a fully actuated hand and then you know
if one of the motors on this dies like I
think one of the benefits of having
tendons is that you know you might
capture some of like the interdependence
between the different degrees of freedom
in the hand is that something that's
like an active kind of ongoing area of
research of how to build in Fault
tolerance in case like one of the motors
dies or something like that that still
allows you to get as much functionality
out of the hand as
possible and then do you want to talk
about that cental paper there's some
working this I think
um I'm not aware of any work which tries
to like build in redundancy into the
joints but what you can do is so if you
can be robust to changing motor
parameters so that that is something
that is very common and we do this in
Locomotion and so on so what you do is
when you're training like let's say you
keep running the hand for several hours
what happens is the motors heat up and
then their properties will change so
they won't respond um to your to Pi like
their gains might change into internally
PID gain typically what we do is when we
train robot policies at least in
simulation we domain randomize over
these parameters so we randomize the
gains randomize the motor strengths and
what happens is if you train an Adaptive
policy then like maybe something like
using like RMA or a recurrent Network
then what happens is that this policy
can learn to use a short history of
joint angles to infer how the properties
have changed and this makes it robust to
changing parameters so that that is I
feel like the dominant approach I don't
know if like if complete failure occurs
then these things would probably not
work and so maybe it's useful to build
redundancy in over there yeah on the
mechanical side also like you're right
the tendons allow like your last two
joints usually they're a lot of times
they're often actuated together so in
Shadow hand and an R leap hand V2
they're actuated as one motor um and
sometimes this compliance can help you
with grasping but yeah if that motor
goes bad then of course you're going to
lose those two of Freedom um I guess one
of the things for us at least has been
we make these hands open source and
they're assemble them yourselves they're
very easy to repair and you can just you
know recalibrate them and it's very
quick to get back up and running and I
know actually many humanoid companies
are taking the same approach um to fault
tance which is if it is really messing
up you just really quickly try to
replace the finger replace the hand and
keep moving I think that's one way to
get around
it that's
okay uh thanks a lot an and Kenny so
this was great I was going to ask a
question on tactile sensing but I think
you sort of already pre-answer it so I
won't ask it again but uh really
appreciate your time what we're going to
do now is my my next lecture is actually
on touch and proception so in case you
are curious to hear that you can stick
around uh it's all it's going to be
about uh human human touch and human
proception it's all about sort of the
neuroscience and psychology of that
which you may or may not care about but
our practice is that we take a break in
the middle of the there's a two-hour
class so we take a break in the middle
so it's now uh 2:40 3:44 my time so
we're going to resume at 34
3:54 okay so there's a 10-minute break
and it's at 3:54 and you guys should not
feel press it to stay you can take off
it's it's up to you okay so thanks let's
thank the
speakers thank you yeah thank you so
much
okay yeah can you send the slides to
toru so she can put it up on our website
yeah I'll send it to her right now
okay okay and recording has started okay
so uh in this
lecture uh I'm going to talk about uh
touch and propri
escription and the hand but the hand
more broadly
construed and uh here is what I want to
convey in this uh in the rest of this
lecture which is that the hand is an
amazing instrument it is
simultaneously a perception device so
kind of like a camera and an actuation
device one which can change the world so
there is a sensory motor
continum of uh the human hand function
and that's what is shown in that top
diagram so at the one end you can think
of it as a measurement device it's it's
tactile sensing so if you think of the
fingers they are a bit like cameras
right they're measuring the world any
object which comes in contact with the
skin
we can measure some stuff from that
there is active haptic sensing by that I
mean you can move the fingers and the
hand over in in various ways so there is
a very simple experiment here that I
want to tell you about which is suppose
you want to know the weight of an
object okay how do you know the weight
of an object so one thing you can do is
you can put your hand on the table okay
and uh I don't know I'm not seeing the
feedback of what people in zoom and L
can see you can put your hand on a table
and then you put the object on it and
you can guess the weight of it right
okay so the way the experiments are done
by psychologist is that you try to
distinguish between two weights so you
have a weight W1 and a weight W2 which
are slightly different and you supposed
to say which one is heavier okay and for
some differences between W1 and W2 you
can make that judgment
reliably okay and for some when the
difference is very small you can't make
it reliably you make it at chance and
the it turns out that that error W1
minus W2 the norm of that that error is
typically proportional to the weight so
this is called a Weber fraction so if
the weight is 100 G then you can
distinguish it from 106 gam if the
weight is 10 gam you can distinguish it
from a weight of 10.6 G something like
that right okay it turns out that so now
you have a way to judge the the the
utility of a hand as a weighing device
it turns out that if you just put your
hand flat on a table where the hand is
stationary and you try to judge weight
you can get a certain accuracy or you
can hold the object in the hand and move
it about okay and you're more accurate
much more accurate that way and the
accuracy is about 6% the Weber fraction
is about 6% so this is active haptic
sensing and then we can talk about the
hand as
an actor the hand as changing the world
in some way and that's and there are we
distinguish between what are called
prehensile movements which involve
grasping and non- prehensile movements
which include everything from gesture
typing piano playing Etc so so this is
the Continuum if you will and the one
end it's a pure sensor measurement
device which does not change the world
it just tries
to learn what the world is about and
then there is the Other Extreme which is
the hand is an action device where you
apply forces and change the
world okay so I'm going to start on the
sensory side of this and I'm going to
start with talking about
proprioception so proprioception is a
genuine discovery of modern science
because uh at least in the in the
western tradition
Aristotle said some things and then
people said okay since Aristotle said
them they must be true and Aristotle
listed five senses s you know Vision
audition touch taste and smell and this
is what kids learn in school in school
they're taught about the five senses and
it really goes back to
Aristotle okay and uh in uh we should
actually do some research on this across
different cultures in Chinese culture or
Indian culture or various other
civilizations do they have the same five
senses I'm not sure I think we are just
being very ethnocentric here and
regarding Aristotle's word as final okay
be as it may uh uh there is this guy
called Charles Bell in 1826 he was a
Scottish scientist and surgeon and who
really studied the hand and so forth and
he proposed a six sense which he called
the muscular
sense and this was subsequently renamed
by sherington as proprioception so what
does that term mean reception receptor
receptor is just some measurement device
proprio means about yourself proprio
it's the same roote as
proprietary property it's like your
personal property it's about you so
proprioception is to be contrasted with
exteroception exteroception is about the
external World proprioception is about
your internal world and the idea of B
and sherington was that even when we
it's in even when it's dark so at night
you wake up from the bed and you don't
have the lights on you know various uh
aspects of your body when my eyes are
closed I can reach and touch my nose
okay I know about the
uh position rough positions of my joints
in some ways and so I know where my body
is and where the parts of my body are
relative to each
other now the question then is how is
this this
implemented what are the how does the
body implemented what's the Neuroscience
of it and uh there then there are that
leads us down two parts one is the
muscular skeletal system in the muscular
skeletal system
how do we know about uh about your your
joint positions velocities Etc and the
answer is that it's because there are
sensors in the muscles and tendons and
joints and my next slide I'm going to uh
give you a figure and then there is the
vestibular system so the vestibular
system is in the inner year and this is
what accounts for your so-called sense
of balance and it has two
components they are the semicircular
canals which
essentially measure your
rotation and then Auto which measure
translation so uh think of uh in your
cell phone your iPhone you have an IMU
which actually does
these that said I'm not going to talk
much about the vestibular system in the
rest of this lecture
sometimes people use the term
kinesthesia and kinesthesia refers to
the the first of these components the
muscular skeletal system now let me get
more
specific so here's a figure which tells
you about about uh kinesthesia or the
proprioception based on the muscular
skeletal system so it's pretty simple
how does the how do we move we have
muscles which are connected by tendons
to bones and then uh there are sensors
inside the muscle
spindle okay and there are a number of
these and uh it they vary according to
the muscle big muscle small muscle so I
actually look this up so the muscle
which enables you to move your index
finger side to side this one this one
has 34 of these okay and your biceps
have 320 of these so there are a precise
number that I can give you of these
these sensors there are also sensors in
the tendon there these are the so-called
G GGI tendon organ so these are sensors
in the tendon which connects the muscle
to the Bone and then there are joint
receptors so joint receptors are like
basically in the skin at the joint and
they are kind of weak they're not very
very accurate they the when the Skins
when you when you when you Flex
or extend a joint then uh what happens
is that the skin at the Joint stretches
and then these sensors detect that so uh
there is a belief that these are mainly
used for you not going out of joint
limits or not breaking your uh joint by
trying to go to far okay so these are
very uh it's pretty straightforward that
the stretching of the muscle is going to
be related to The Joint angle and if you
can measure that and that that signal in
the nerve that's going to be useful to
the brain for figuring out joint
angles uh okay so I think I dealt with
the muscular skeletal system sensors in
the muscles tendons and the
joints okay uh now what about robots
Okay I think you got a bit of the sense
of this uh in the previous lecture and
in the in the even more previous lecture
where we talked about uh robot
kinematics and Dynamics so uh so I will
just do the simpleminded story here so
the simpleminded story is that suppose
we are using Motors well then what is a
motor we are using these electric motors
so electric motors have shafts which
rotate so therefore you want to know the
angular position and those are uh
there's a a rotary encoder will sense
that angle okay so that gives you
measurement of the the equivalent uh
thing in the that in the human body it's
achieved by these senses in the muscles
and the tendons and so
forth okay uh now uh what's the sense of
touch so that Aristotle did know about
the sense of touch so that was in his
list of five so how do we Define this uh
so uh it's it's it's an amazing system I
mean I I knew a little bit of about it
but then I took the trouble to study it
more extensively in the last couple of
months and it's super impressive I was a
vision chauvinist I always believed that
vision is the most remarkable of Senses
because uh it's it is uh very very
sensitive and yet it operates over a
dynamic range so in the case of vision
you have like 100 million receptors a
single receptor can detect a single
Photon that's like the smallest you can
get and and then it can operate in
bright sunlight so that's like a dynamic
range of 11 orders of magnitude it has
very good spatial Precision temporal
Precision Etc but I've been impressed by
the sense of touch it's actually in some
ways it's even more remarkable than
Vision okay how does it work though very
important Point here is that the skin is
flexible so when you press on any s any
surface when a when an object presses
against your finger for example or
what's happening is that the skin is
stretched and the area in contact
increases it increases by can be as much
as like 70% so it's a significant
increase other features on the finger
which are useful there are
fingerprints so these fingerprints help
provide friction so when you are holding
some surface which is like wet or
slippery then actually they come in
handy so okay so really it starts from
the skin
itself and then there will be some
mechanical deformation of the skin
because you have applied some some
pressure on the skin maybe in a
localized way and this is detected by
so-called mechano
receptors what does that term mean
mechano means mechanics mechanical that
that's a word right receptor is just
like uh we already saw in the context of
photo receptors photo receptors measure
light mechano receptors measure some
mechanical
change okay here is a slide which shows
uh uh uh what they are and where they
located so there is the skin that we
have it's of two types it's they
so-called hairy skin and well I would
have called it non-hairy skin but the
biologists use the term glabra skin so
the canonical example of that is the
skin on your palm the skin on skin on
your on the Palmer side is which of
these gabas the skin on the other side
the dorsal side is hairy skin okay uh
okay so the most sensitive areas are
typically glabra skin okay the fingertip
is a very sensitive area the lips are a
very sensitive area okay and underneath
what you have are these various uh uh
types here there's the so-called let me
see if my mouse works yeah okay so let's
go through the the names there are four
names to know here the Merkel
dis receptor the mner corporel so most
of these are named after Germans or
Italians from the 19th century these two
are Germans and then there is
ruini and then there's Pini okay so
there are four types of uh so they the
these folks got their names because they
discovered their sometime in the late
19th century so okay so let's try to
remember the names mner corporel
Merkel dis receptor okay eventually the
names are not important but what
question so you mentioned before Vision
sense and I feel like for vision like
most of the Heavenly things is not by
the eye but actually by the BR so the
same is true here it will always be the
case we we do not see just with our eyes
we see with our brain the same we do not
touch just with our touch but with our
brain yeah that's always the case yeah
okay so the so let's
see okay so the the mner corpal and the
Merk dis receptor the thing you should
notice that they are high up they are
pretty close to the skin surface then
deep down is where you have these this
uh uh pacinian Corpus
and the ruini endings so these are
slightly
lower and this you can immediately guess
what that implies right so there'll be a
more close more delicate spatial
sensitivity and resolution in the sensor
which are closer to the to the epidermis
right so the Merkel and the mner will
have more fine grain spatial uh
resolution whereas the pacinian corpor
and the Rini ending since they are lower
down they're going to be kind of
integrating over a larger area of the of
the of the skin so that you can
intuitively guess just from the
anatomy okay uh now uh so when the skin
is pressed there is some activation
right of these various sensors just like
when light hits your eye there is an
activation of these these photo
receptors and then the photo recept so
the photo receptor it there's a photon
that is received and then some
electrical signal is produced and then
it is Shi through the optic nerve to the
brain so the same kind of thing is going
to happen in the context of of touch
okay and then our brain is what where
the perception occurs right so in the
case of light that single Photon leads
to the subjective perception of
something twinkling in your visual field
well here it going to be perceived as
some kind of touch or pressure or
whatever
okay there are other receptors
underneath the skin which send warmth
cold pain itching and these are
important for human survival but I won't
say more about them okay I'm focusing on
the the ones which are going to be more
useful from a robotics point of
view okay so now we we had these four
sensors uh so there are uh merel mner
right uh ruini endings and pacinian
corpuses and the first Yeah
question things can
sense pressure that they go through the
same nerves close to the skin or the
same sensory structures sense multiple
things or are they all no no they
they're never see what happens with s is
that they get activated by certain
stimuli and then then there is a nerve
impulse which goes on that on from that
nerve and then it is bundled up and it's
received ultimately by the somato
sensory cortex and it's a job of the
somat sensory cortex to interpret what
is happened and and uh let me make an
analogy with color vision so in the case
of color vision what's happening is that
there are three different receptor types
but all three receptors are activated
whenever you see some scene but they are
differentially activated and it's a job
of the brain to interpret the
differential outputs of the different
receptors to to perceive the
SE okay do you ever have like one nerve
that's receiving
information that can happen yeah you can
you can obviously merge I mean in the in
the visual system whenever I don't know
details about the about the Touch system
I'm going to use Vision as an example
because I know that well okay so in the
case of vision we start with 120 million
receptors and the optic nerve has just a
million
fibers but you never have like a nerve
in
the you have various stages of
processing yeah okay so uh so back to
this picture so there's a concept of
receptive field in neuroscience and
receptive field field in neural networks
so receptive field for a neuron refers
to what what are so in the case of say
uh neural network which is processing
visual information the receptive field
of a neuron refers to which are the
pixels in the input which if you change
you can change the output of that neuron
so we can talk about the receptive
fields at every stage of a neural
network and at the early stages the
receptive feeds are small and at the
higher stages the receptive feed are
large right so initially they might just
respond to a vertical line in a few
pixels at the late stages they might
respond to a face anywhere okay so uh
the receptive fields of these uh Merkel
discs and mes Corpus Sals are small you
can see that in the diagram here right
they're all small so they're quite
acutely sensitive
to something like the density of these
uh I think these mer receptors might be
like every 1 mm or so
okay then these
uh these uh on the other hand these
ruini endings and pacinian corpos they
are
deeper in the sense of underneath lower
down the skin and then they have big
receptive Fields as as shown is shown in
this figure okay so that's one so
spatial resolution these top two are as
low spatial resolution which means that
they'll be useful for fine spatial
discrimination the bottom two will be
less useful for fine spatial
discrimination the other dimension is
temporal frequency so do they do the
responses change when the input changes
because you can have because you know if
you go back to your uh whatever your
first signals class on forier transforms
low spatial frequencies high spatial
frequencies similarly you can talk about
low temporal frequencies and high
temporal frequencies so uh between these
the uh there's this term sa and uh ra a
so what you guess sa stands for slowly
adapting and ra is rapidly adapting so
which one should deal with fast
changes rapidly adapting good so our
colleagues know how to name their
systems well okay so so so when you have
for example a steady uh so in the case
of let's look at MERS corpuses so they
are rapidly
adapting what that means is that when
there is some when I press something on
the skin as soon as that event happens
there is a sharp change and uh so it's
going to respond it very fast okay so
now if you look at the bottom this is
the spike train so the spike train of uh
of this ra1 ra1 here is M corpuses so
ra1 as soon as there is
a a stimulus which is shown here so the
stimulus was zero and then it jumped up
so there's like a step change as soon as
that change occurs you got lots of
spikes right and then once it became
steady then it stops so it doesn't
respond to steady change so it's like
you need high frequencies in the
temporal Dimension to keep this neuron
firing if when it becomes constant it
doesn't care so constant steady pressure
it doesn't it doesn't care now this is
not true for example for the Merkle
discs where uh a steady uh pressure is
it's still responding to that so this
combo of these four types low spatial
frequencies low SP small receptive
Fields versus large receptive Fields
rapidly acting versus slow acting that
combination gives you that kind of
diversity of responses such that after
that the brain can do whatever
interpretation it does so again my
analogy is that to color you have three
different photo receptor types which are
sensitive to light different spectral
distributions of light and the
combination of the three responses gives
us a very good signal yeah now there
were some question which I can answer
now yeah
yeah correct yeah exactly event camera
is a good
analogy oh that I want to get get into
but look it up okay yeah
question multiple re Fields correct yeah
yeah multiple small ones yeah okay so
now I have a example here from this book
uh touch the the science of hand heart
and mind so this guy comes up with some
good cool examples of how which sensors
are being activated actually everyone is
being activated but which is more
important so so so the task is the
following so I'm I park my car I need to
fish a quarter out of my pocket well now
you might use your cell phone but in the
era when you had to put coins into
parking meters so first you reach into
your pocket in your pocket there are
some coins there are your keys there's
your wallet there's your cell phone and
you have to fish something out what are
you going to do you're essentially
solving an object recognition problem
with your fingers but uh what's likely
to be the the most useful signal to
distinguish for example a quarter from
the DI so if you think about it the most
useful is clearly the mercur disc
because sharp edges are going to be
detected very nicely by the by by the by
the the Merkle disc they're going to
respond and by feeling the boundaries of
objects you will find that round kind of
thing which is the qu okay the second
task is now you found that coin you fish
it out of your pocket I should have had
a coin in my pocket okay I'll fake it
with a pencil imagine that there is a
quarter now I what's happening there so
now it's steady right so I'm the the the
mer dis is not is giving me a steady
signal but the mner is actually quite
useful because if my if I don't apply
the right amount of force I apply two
little Force what's going to happen it's
going to start to slip if it's going to
start to slip that's going to activate
the the the the the rapidly adapting
receptors the MERS they are going to
fire right because they fire whenever
you have sharp changes and then in a
very quick Loop the brain gets the
signal and responds to it and and what
you do is when you start it starts to
slip you just apply more force and you
when you apply more normal force there's
going to be a greater frictional
resistance and then the object will no
longer slip and this is happening sort
of
subconsciously so we are we are when we
hold objects we don't apply huge amounts
of force we apply just the right amount
of force so the force when you hold up
an egg right you don't want to be
applying huge amounts of force when you
are doing rock climbing and you're
hanging by your fingers you better apply
enough Force otherwise you're going to
fall off and die right so that kind of
adaptation is based on sensory feedback
and this is something we would love to
give our robots
Okay and then you insert the coin and
then you now what's happening is that
now the response is essentially directed
towards your full finger or hand and
it's now uh it's now more distributed
and at this point your these other this
uh pan corpor Sals are going to be
useful for you okay
yeah yeah
brain directly or
does I mean we we don't know the full
details but but there is we we can do
psychophysics to judge how good humans
are a discriminating and they can
discriminate two stimula which are about
a millimeter apart on the finger and
that is roughly the same as the spacing
of the sensors in the in the fingers so
it's like in your eye you can
distinguish simula which fall on one
cone versus the next cone over and
something
similar so we are not so where we care
about Exquisite spatial sensitivity such
as on the tips of our fingers the system
doesn't build something fancy and after
that Lose It by averaging it away it
makes full use of
it okay uh okay so I think you you this
example is now done now what happens is
that now somebody asked me do we see
with the uh when we see do we see with
our eyes or do we see with our brains
and the answer is you obviously see with
both I mean if you didn't have the
photons falling on your eyes you
wouldn't have anything to start with but
the process is all the stages matter so
the stages in the so this is a slide
which shows what's happening in the
brain so in the brain there is a uh so
the term used is somato sensory cortex
so the somato sensory cortex is getting
the signal from these nerves which are
going from the hand then they go through
the spinal cord they go up to the brain
and the somat sensory cortex is kind of
in this this area of the brain it's it's
near the so-called Central sulcus okay
of the cerebral cortex and uh and this
is next to uh the the somato sensory
area how do we know that there is a
somato sensory area so the the neurons
there are activated when you activate
various parts of your skin maybe your
fingers maybe your tongue maybe your
lips maybe your you push a pin on your
back etc etc right so that that's how
you you can map out the somato sensory
cortex and uh the somato sensory cortex
very conveniently is right next to the
motor cortex so let let me show this
figure so in this figure if you look
there is the somato sensory cortex and
it's right next to this other strip
which is the motor cortex so the motor
cortex is the one where there are
neurons which uh which fire when you
decide to move your hand and pick up an
object and so on so it looks like the
brain is doing the sensible thing in
terms of the wiring so you're getting
this input from the the sensors in on
your fingers and so forth as well as
proprioceptive input from your muscles
and so forth It's all used together and
then it is triggering action in the
motor cortex where you're causing
activations of the muscles which move
your arms and thumbs and fingers and so
forth yeah that thing learned from
interaction or is it like a static it is
not fully static but it is it is
somewhat uh it's somewhat repeated from
person to person but there are these
classic experiments which show where uh
which show that when
you on both the motor side and the
sensory side if you use something more
so like
pianist so their representation of the
fingers is going to be will take up more
area okay you can do things like of
course you can do cruel things like chop
off a finger and the representation of
that finger will shrivel and other other
areas will sort of take up those neurons
so there is plasticity in the Contex and
it was first established in this
setting okay what I show here is what is
sometimes referred to as the sensory
motor
homunculus and this is like from uh this
guy of Penfield who was doing these
experiments around 1950s for people who
had epileptic seizures they would cut
open their skull and they would have to
do some stuff to reduce the risk of
seizures but when they were doing that
they would be able to do experiments on
them so it turns out that the entire
body skin surface is represented on the
somato sensory cortex but not all parts
have equal importance so that the area
the real estate in the somato sensory
cortex is partitioned out according to
importance so uh so you see uh you see
there's a lot here corresponding to wait
let me see so like the the hand the
fingers the thumb the forearm elbow now
you see there like the legs not so much
not so much is being used up there okay
there's a lot being used up for the face
and so forth right so this is on the
sensory side and this is on the motor
side on the motor side again you have a
so this is like what neurons are
activating when they are firing then
some finger moves or something like that
or the your elbow joint changes from
flexion to
extension so that okay so that's this
this is just roughly giving you a sense
of the importance of the different areas
which is roughly related to the density
of senses so if you think in Vision in
Vision we talk about the phobia so in
the phobia you have a much greater
density of photo receptors corresponding
to a certain visual angle and then as
you go into the periphery you have a
lower density of photo receptors what's
the equivalent of the phobia for the
skin tactile system it's like the finger
the fingers have very high density right
whereas the back your the skin on your
back has much lower density of of these
receptors okay okay so that was uh one
point next point is that these all these
areas in the on the cerebral cortex they
have names and numbers I mean so like
the visual areas are called V1 V2 V3 V4
so here they have all these areas called
M1 M2 so there people are not super
inspired but that's good because that's
unes us to remember them M1 M2 refers to
like the motor cortex areas one two what
do you think this s
suggests somato sensory yeah and then
there are numbers and then there are uh
there are these kinds of uh wiring
diagrams which tell you how the input
comes in so the input comes in from the
skin through the thalamus so the
thalamus is like a V station before it
gets to the cortex then you have this
this uh uh somato sensory cortex and
then and then after that there are these
two stream
one called the ventral stream and one
called the dorsal stream and this is
kind of interesting because again I will
refer back to my my vision experience
people have constructed diagrams like
this for the visual system okay so
whenever I'm at a loss to understand the
somato sensory system I just refer back
to the visual system so in the case of
visual system the visual system people
have made these diagrams up which
correspond to the different areas of the
cortex starting from kind of the retina
basically the rgc is retinal gangan cell
and then there are these various areas
of the brain and what's connected to
what okay and uh but the next part is
kind of interesting which is that the
after the early generic visual
processing areas you get two streams one
which is called the dorsal stream and
one which is called the ventral stream
okay the ventral stream is very easy to
uh describe so the ventral stream which
so dorsal and ventral dorsal means on
the back ventral means towards the front
so you can see the arrows so this is
supposed to be a view of the of the of
the of the head where the back is on the
on the on the right hand side
okay so the ventral pathway leads to uh
what's called inferior temporal cortex
this is where object recognition happens
and face recognition happens and so on
okay and then there is this dorsal
pathway which you can see where it's
going it's going to the same area where
you have somato sensory cortex and motor
cortex so that should give you a clue
it's like trying okay so this was
sometimes described as a where pathway
but some people just use the term the
how pathway because it's about it's
really about vision for action and when
you want vision for Action what do you
want to put together you want to put
together Vision you want to put together
the mapping from proprioception the
mapping from touch and then you want to
have it next door to the motor cortex
which is where you activate the various
muscles so it's all all makes sense you
want to be neighbors to the people whom
you want to influence Yeah
question so yes the ventral pathway you
can think of as basically to me all
these these large language models or
lbms or what VMS so VMS are vental
pathway so the people who insist that
all of intelligence is solved by VMS I
completely disagree of course but but uh
but they're basically focusing on just
this part so when you have GPT for o or
V or whatever what it does is it it
takes an image recognizes some objects
converts it to some tokens and then it's
the rest is all mush together with
language well that is the ventral
pathway but that is missing out the
dorsal pathway which is very important
if you didn't have the dorsal pathway
you wouldn't have survived because the
value I mean Vision guides action and
that's that's how you you live I mean
you go to find food and so on okay so uh
so here's the cool part you have these
two streams also from
the the the the proprioceptive and uh uh
tactile uh information so there are two
streams here notice that there is a
ventral
stream and there's a dorsal Stream So
the ventral stream what is that that is
the hand as a sensor when I go to a
store and I'm looking at some fabric and
there's some silk and
I'm running my fingers over it and I'm
trying to judge is it is it nice smooth
silk or not that's a judgment of of a
material property
right that's a that's not immediately
guiding action it is guiding perception
it's like attributes of various objects
so our attributes or objects are judged
visually but also through
your proprioceptive and somat sensory uh
systems okay and then there's this other
pathway the dorsal stream and this is
going to for example when this object
starts to slip and you need to
immediately act well that's clearly that
other stream so both streams are
important both exist for vision both
also exist in this
uh setting of uh Pro receptive
information and touch
information okay so this is the so this
is a summary of what I said so far uh so
there's the what system which is kind of
recognizing objects and measuring their
attributes and then there is the wear
system which you could think of a
spatial location but actually more
importantly it's guiding action it's the
house
system uh so I think I somebody asked me
a question so I already said this the
vental stream connects to
multimodal conscious
perception object names attributes VMS
so VM M are the ventral stream the
dorsal stream connects to action and
this is in the spirit of perception
guides action so today's lecture is all
about
proprioception but the next lecture is
going to be about Vision guides action
so basically I'm going to be talking
about the dorsal stream with respect to
Vision that'll be uh next week's first
lecture uh and I have the example of
slip but there are many others there's
just one example
so any question on
this somebody in if they if there's a
question on chat you should no nothing
okay
yeah no no I I I think this is in
they're in primat yeah but I I I don't
know enough to tell you about what there
are different animals uh among different
mammals uh the emphas the importance of
different systems varies so for example
rats pay much more attention to the
somato sensory system right they're uh
so they have these whiskers and with
this whisking movement they they are
measuring properties of the world so we
are visual animals but not all animals
are visual uh I mean they they they all
have these different capabilities but uh
bats are relying more on audition you
know we are relying on Vision rats are
relying more on somato sensory and so
forth
Yeah
question can you speak louder
please yeah no so so I'm I'm saying that
so that may come in through more higher
level planning okay so when we think of
action again we don't know the details
for sure but my rough speculation would
be something like this so there is
action is always hierarchical and at
multiple time scales so there needs to
be some action that you're taking at 100
Herz some at 10 Herz some at 1 Herz so
the decision that I make which is that I
need to go get a cup of coffee is
operating on a slow time scale and it
may be that it got triggered because I
saw some ad of somebody with with a nice
cup of coffee right okay as opposed to
something which is happening at 10 Herz
or 100 HZ which is when I'm holding the
coffee cup and I don't want it to slip
so so conscious perception obviously
plays a role in guiding actions at a
more higher level just may not be doing
so at the very fast control loop at 10
HZ or 100
HZ yeah and we don't lot of this is the
particularly these higher kind of layers
we we just not enough is known from the
Neuroscience yeah
yeah okay so I'll repeat the question
for people in Zoom which is that uh
given the sophistication and complexity
of the Touch system in humans uh where
do we stand today in
robotics and the answer is we are far
very far back so my way of saying this
is that uh in Vision we are in robotic
Vision in terms of the hardware we are
as good as humans or even better but in
robotic touch no so that means that over
the next few years there will be
significant advances that need to occur
uh which uh which will enable us to have
better sensors so it's right now the
situation seems to be the there are just
not that many people working in this
area so in my view the area of tactile
sensing just needs lots more
research and uh one of the issues was
that in the past we if people built
these sensors they didn't know how to
use them well I think that with uh the
benefit of the deep learning techniques
in
robotics we have much more advances in
how to use these kinds of
sensors so I think that that now when
people build these sensors we actually
find good ways of using them and and
what you need is this virtuous cycle
where uh somebody builds good sensors
you use it and good policies people are
impressed by the results then they feel
motivated to put in more money in
research on better sensing and so forth
and advances can come from anywhere
electrical engineering Material Science
mechanical engineering
everywhere but is a good point
okay so let's go back to the sensory
motor Continuum of human hand function
and I
spent I I I gave you like the basic
sensory Hardware so that was valid for
Passive tactile sensing if I kept my
hand stationary and I just put a object
on it or I move an object on it this is
passive tectile sensing now I want to
refer to active haptic sensing where you
choose to move the sensors so you choose
to move the hand so my example earlier
was I have an object I want to know how
much it weighs or whether it weighs
heavier or lighter than object a between
object a and object B so I'm going to
put it in my hand and I will move it up
and down and I'll I can do a better job
that way so this is what we mean by
active heptic sensing so I do not wish
to at all imply that vision is always
passive vision is also active and in the
case of vision it comes from the fact
that we have a phobia so when I I my
attention can be attracted from anywhere
in the room if somebody asks me a
question I'm going to turn my head and
my eyes to look at that person so we
fiate and that is
active uh sensing other examples are I'm
looking at some image and I'm doing
visual search I'm trying to find
something so Active Vision Vision also
is not just passive it's also active
okay uh in the case of uh
touch uh the same thing so the the the
the the slogan here is that it's not the
the the the the merkal receptors which
are your which which which is what
achieve touch it's the hand that achieve
touch and the hand that achieves touch
through the combination of the active
movement of the hand okay and and then
of course the measurements that you get
from the
senses is that
clear so let's let's go into okay I've
given you the basic examples but now I
want to play this for
you my
favorite The Lion the Witch and the
Wardrobe once there were four children
whose names were Peter Susan Edmond and
Lucy foxes said Edmond rabbits said
Susan but when next morning came there
was a steady rain falling of course it
would be raining said Edmund my name is
Mary Wagner and I'm the Braille
instructor here I've been reading
Braille since I was three years old it
is a major passion of mine and I'm so
excited that I get to teach it every
single day reading is just essential
anyway um unfortunately a lot of blind
children fall through the cracks because
um they're not exposed to bral at a
young age I was actually very very
blessed my vision teacher sat down with
me three years old and began to teach me
the Braille alphabet if it weren't for
Braille I can't even imagine where I
would be education Wise It's just like
the print on the page that cited people
can read rail is a way for you to get
the same information so that that story
that that child really wants to read
they can read that same story that their
friends are reading the only difference
is they use it with their fingers
instead of their eyes if I were to
explain it to an adult I would say it's
a series of dot
combinations so there's six dots and
each dot has its own number a is do one
B is do 1 and two c is 14 D is 145 and
as you progress in learning the letters
there's a slight pattern and it kind of
starts to make a little more sense so I
wouldn't say it's mathematical it's just
a matter of getting the shape um in your
mind and and letting your fingers do the
reading this is the stylus what this is
doing is punching the holes in the paper
and this is the Slate each one of these
little squares they have six little
holes inside them that mimics the
Braille cell so the reason you're
writing from right to left is because
when you turn the paper over you're
going to read from left to right if I'm
writing a long document it's just more
conducive for me to use the brail writer
this is
one23 and this is 4 5 6 so you're only
using these three fingers you'll see why
I like this better I mean it's a lot
louder but I can get a lot more
accomplished with
this no parent of any sided child would
be content with their child just
listening to um an audible recording
they they want their children to read if
your child is blind they have the same
right to learn how to read as a cited
child and with technology being what it
is they have Braille displays so that
any book um can be in a digital format
and trans ated into Braille by using the
Braille displays Braille could
definitely be taught um to someone who
is not blind just like there are classes
for communities you know in uh sign
language there's there should definitely
be something like that available for
those who are interested in learning
Braille because like you said you never
know if your vision is going to go
reading is amazing I have had a lot of
experiences in my life where I've been
able to just become a part of the story
I I've always loved stor stories so the
fact that I can have the same access to
information as any cited person um who
loves to read it's it's it's definitely
a blessing I'm thankful that it's
available for the
blind
okay okay so uh so of course there's an
emotional aspect to seeing this but uh
now we can be all nerdy and Engineering
about it uh but here are some numbers on
how impressive this capability is so
first of all you you got the the that
key technical point right six binary so
therefore 2 to the^ 6 if you think of
the the alphabet it is 26 letters
probably there are all the digits so you
can see how it would work out and so
this fellow Braille was a french guy who
worked it out about 1820s 1830s
something like that there used to be
some other system but he figured out
essenti what's a good coding
system and uh and and then it took a
while before it got accepted and uh but
it has got accepted but average bail
readers can read at 120 words per minute
and experts at 200 words per
minute okay and this corresponds to
recognizing a a character at 50
millisecond and to see how impressive
this is uh when you are cited readers
like people like us
uh our reading speed is 240 wordss per
minute so it's like a fact of two only a
loss of a fact of two compared to this
very I mean what you what your system
has to do and uh if you had to guess
which which of the four receptors are
being used
here so this is a test of your memory or
or your quality of your
notes huh the mark Merkle because it's
high spatial resolution because you're
moving the finger so you don't have to
worry about the the the fast part so
that it's the Merk receptors which are
which have the highest spatial
resolution but everything is being
activated and the Brain interprets okay
so this is I so this is active right
you're moving your finger in a program
and we do that the same is true for
visual reading we also and we and and
and and there's more here about which I
I don't know how much you know how well
studied this area is because in visual
normally when we read we do not actually
read every letter we read uh I I looked
into this some years ago we look 40% of
the way into the letter because we have
phation I mean here there is a phobia
which is your finger but for the human
reader also there's a there's a phobia
and you want to put the phobia not at
the first letter of the word but 40% of
the ve because that way you get enough
of enough letters that you can guess the
word and then you move on so we do not
actually painstakingly get every
character we we get enough to guess and
then we move on and as you know from the
success of llms there's a lot of
redundancy in English and as you have
learned as you become good readers you
you read fast because you have your your
cognitive system is guiding that
somebody had a question yeah
video they're like kind of rubing it's
not just
like sliding I think I thought of it I
saw it more as sliding
yeah super resolution that way by like
you know
inter getting like on like the
boundaries of your different like
receptors and things like this or like
do they know why this is
useful honestly I I I I don't know I've
not uh
my my knowledge of Braille is what like
this video captures my knowledge of bra
I read a little bit more about the
history of Braille because that was
interesting and uh but uh I
I there would presumably have been some
I mean what I would look for are papers
in this business from some psychologist
trying to analyze this and you would
have to do controlled experiments but I
just don't know the literature fa
enough okay uh okay here
uh here is a paper this is an old paper
from leaderman and katski this I think
it I gave you a few examples I gave you
the example of reading where there is a
procedure being followed I give you the
example of weighing an object where
there's a procedure being followed so
leaderman and classi what they tried to
do was they gave people many different
tasks and then from that they tried to
abstract if there were a common set of
procedures which are being used and this
is their list so the first uh one is
this lateral motion which is if you if I
ask you to judge the texture is it like
uh rough paper or smooth paper so what
you do is you just move your fingers on
the
surface okay unsupported holding weight
okay I think we already talked about
that moving the hand up and down uh
pressure what would you do if you ask
you whether it was hard or soft you
press your finger down on it right or
multiple fingers down on the object
enclosure volume you would just so so so
think of all these experiments being
done in the without Vision you can do
these experiments in with the eyes shut
right okay you can guess the volume
static contact temperature so uh uh yeah
so that's that's easy you're activating
the temperature by the way this is quite
helpful and for an interesting reason
why does uh if you have have a piece of
aluminum versus a piece of wood why does
the aluminum feel
colder it's a conductor because it's a
conductor so the heat is conducted away
so it feels cold so so in a way it's
just a proxy to sort of heat
conductivity which is correlated also to
electrical conductivity Contour
following so this is like instead of
volume you go around the boundary of the
object I mean I I wouldn't take this
literally as okay these are the six and
there'll be variance it could be eight
but it the important idea here is that
there are policies being followed which
are just for getting good
perception you're trying to answer
perceptual questions what's the weight
of the object is it a hard object is it
a smooth surface and you execute a a
procedure hence exploratory procedure
yeah
I mean we are
primates probably I I I don't know the
answer to whether somebody has done that
experiment but my guess would be yes
because the touch systems are very
similar these are not
different uh okay okay so I think I
think I I've covered so so these two the
the two on the left were really the hand
as
a sensing device so the hand is like a a
camera based on touch if you will touch
and prop perception because when you're
are moving your that object in your palm
up and down you're also getting uh Force
measurements and so forth from the
sensors and your the muscular skeletal
system right the muscle spindles and and
in the GGI tendon organs and so on they
are also being activated and now let's
to the action side which is now the hand
as
a as something which acts in the world
and uh we can distinguish between what
are called prehensile movements and non-
prehensile movements and prehensile
refers to uh grasping basically Pan the
word just means grasping and uh and
there's a uh classic uh paper on this
from Napier in 1956 actually there was a
someone called shinger in Germany who
wrote some papers in the 20s on this but
uh some of napia classification is the
one which caught on and uh you can in
fact whenever there's a classification
or category tonomy you can choose how
deep to go but the highest level is this
distinction between a power grip and a
Precision grip power grasp or Precision
grasp the power grasp you can see what
that is right that's where you apply a
lot of force and then there is uh
Precision grip where between the thumb
and the four finger okay and uh in
children which of these do you think
develops
first power grip right so because they
they once they start to be able to open
their their hand they are able to do
this and uh I think of it as if you if
you did uh principal component analysis
suppose you had tons and tons of uh
photos of people uh doing grasping
movements in the real world or even just
movements involving the hands and then
you try to find the first principal
component what's the most commonly used
degree of Freedom it's going to be this
one okay and this actually accounts for
the success of parallel jog rippers so
parallel jog rippers that people in
robotics use and I hate because in my
view those are I mean we want to get to
dexterous manipulation and parallel
jogers is like it should be like 20th
century not 21st century but parallel
jog rers capture the most
common degree of Freedom that you want
with your hands which is this this
movement right the the the power
grasp okay but we want to do lot more
subtle stuff that's why we want to use
multi-finger hands and so
on okay uh this list is by no means
exhaustive there is a book that I have
it's uh I'm showing it here but for the
people in Zoom they can just see that uh
so this is from someone called noro
Kamakura and I think of her as like
having done the best work in this area
of understanding the movements of the
hand and sadly all this work was in
Japanese and not known to people in the
west who came up with their own various
hierarchies of grasps and so on which
are all actually inferior to the work
that that she did like in the 70s and
80s okay but anyway this work has been
translated in English and is now
available so what she did was a very uh
careful study of how we use our hands in
daily life so I worked on this project
called ego 4D so she did like that ego
4D kind of thinking except she was doing
it in the '70s
what she did was she made a list of what
are common objects and what are common
verbs corresponding to Common actions
and then she brought people in the lab
and she had this list of okay these are
the common objects and these are the
common actions and then she had a way of
identifying what parts of the hand are
touching the object very simple just put
some ink on the object and then when you
hold the object then your fingers will
have the ink and uh and now you have
recorded what parts were in contact so
uh anyway I I'm not sure if I believe in
the strict taxonomy but the value of the
taxonomy is to show the variety of ways
in which we use our hands and we don't
use our hand just one hand at a time we
use B manual we use multiple hands at
the same
time
only for example for one particular
object or no it depends on what you want
to do with it so the my canonical
example this is a coffee mug okay
there's a coffee
mug when I'm drinking from it there's a
way I hold the coffee mug when I want to
hand it to you there's a way I hold a
coffee mug when I want to put it into a
dishwasher there's a way I hold the
coffee mug when I take it out of the
dishwasher and I want to put it in my
cabinet all of these are different it's
the same damn coffee mug right so grasps
are always functional and therefore they
can vary and and again
uh
yeah okay now I uh to end the lecture I
think I'm within five minutes four
minutes so okay that that's great uh and
now I want to talk about so this is what
we talked about how we use the hands for
manipulating objects so and and I I I
didn't I've chosen not to go into too
much detail here because basically we're
going to do later in the class the use
of dexterous hands for uh various kinds
of manipulation tasks so now I want to
end in the last three four minutes of
this class with how we use our hands not
necessarily just for manipulation which
is for communication and there are
theories which say that in fact the
communication with gesture might have
been the Prelude to language okay so
conversational gesture so these are
slides from some old project that Shiri
and I and a few others were involved in
but have uh uh videos from this which
are fun to watch so the first thing to
note is that uh that uh uh hand how we
use a gestures accompanying language is
actually of different types there sign
language which is a full-fledged
language okay it has a grammar it's a
syntax it's it's like it's like spoken
language is it okay uh and then you have
gesture which accompany speech so when
I'm talking I cannot but
emit uh you know I I can't help it I'm
moving am I my hands are moving in line
with this then there is what is called
italianate gesture which I think is
self-explanatory but I will give you a
video so first let's talk about sign
language pandel has taught us the power
of action but he also taught us the
power of
ideas okay okay so that's sign language
so there's somebody who's interpreting
so there is his English speech and then
there is the equivalent of that in sign
language which is I so I think here the
fun problems are when will we give
robots the ability to speak in Sign
Language okay we should be able to do it
okay there are some papers to be written
here okay and then uh I will end my
lecture with I will end with Italian
G what come
on full of
people I thought there was more in there
okay anyway you can find more on this on
the web but at this thank you very much